<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary-le-Bow, to the societies for reformation of manners, Octob. 2, 1699 by Samuel Barton ; published at the request of the said societies.</title>
            <author>Barton, Samuel, 1647 or 8-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B994</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32551</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12716298</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12716298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66240</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31113)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66240)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1030:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Mary-le-Bow, to the societies for reformation of manners, Octob. 2, 1699 by Samuel Barton ; published at the request of the said societies.</title>
                  <author>Barton, Samuel, 1647 or 8-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matthew Wotton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Mary-le-Bow,</hi> TO THE SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of Manners,</hi> Octob. 2. 1699.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SAMUEL BARTON,</hi> D.D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the ſaid SOCIETIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Mathew Wotton,</hi> at the Three <hi>Daggers</hi> near the <hi>Temple-gate</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66240:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPH. v. xi.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but rather reprove them.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>BEING deſired to Preach one of the Quarterly Sermons <hi>For Reformation of Manners,</hi> I muſt own, that the greateſt Motive I had to induce me not to refuſe, was the Conſideration, that if I ſhou'd, I thought I might fall under a juſt Reproof from this which I have read, and other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel Texts of Scripture, which require us to be ſo far from partaking with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in Sin, that we ſhou'd rather ſet our ſelves to oppoſe it all we can. And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66240:3"/>tho' I cannot pretend to add any thing to what has been already ſaid by ſome Right Reverend Fathers, and others my Reverend and Worthy Brethren upon this Subject; Yet, as I take it for an Honour to appear in ſo excellent a Cauſe, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſo good Company; ſo I hope, that tho' but the ſame things in ſubſtance that have been ſaid before be repeated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and in a more homely Dreſs, it may yet have ſome good effect, and help, in ſome degree to farther that excellent End, which both as Men, and as Chriſtians we are all bound to ſeek the Promotion of, even the beating down of Vice and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs, and the Encreaſe of Piety and Virtue.</p>
            <p>Without farther Preface therefore, I ſhall proceed to ſpeak to the Words of the Text. And in ſo doing I ſhall,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Shew you what is meant by <hi>Works of Darkneſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. Why they are ſo call'd.</item>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66240:3"/>
               <item>III. Why they are ſaid to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and how well that Character agrees to 'em.</item>
               <item>IV. I ſhall explain to you what is meant by having <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> with ſuch <hi>Works,</hi> and what are the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Ways and ſeveral Inſtances wherein Men are tempted to have that. And,</item>
               <item>V. I ſhall ſhew, That Chriſtians ſhou'd have a care of being drawn in by any ſuch Temptations, and inſtead of that ſhou'd upon all occaſions ſhew their utter diſlike of theſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and be ready to reprove them, and to prevent as far as poſſible the Commiſſion of them. Of which Doctrine I ſhall in the laſt place make ſome brief Application to the preſent Occaſion. I begin with the Firſt, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. To ſhew what is meant by <hi>Works of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66240:4"/>Darkneſs.</hi> And here all will agree with me, that by <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> Works of Sin and Wickedneſs are meant, and that of the more groſs and heinous ſort. Sin every one ought to know (for 'tis the Definition given by St. <hi>John</hi>) 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.4. is nothing elſe but <hi>A Tranſgreſſion of the Law.</hi> And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Where no Law is there is no Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion,</hi> or no Sin. But nevertheleſs all Sins are not alike, or of equal guilt or heinouſneſs in their nature. And that becauſe there is a difference in Laws, a difference in the manner of their Promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and a difference in the manner al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of our tranſgreſſing 'em. There is a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Laws: For ſome are concerning things of greater weight and moment than others are, and upon which the Law-giver is therefore ſuppos'd to lay a greater ſtreſs than he does upon others. And hence the Violation of ſuch Laws is ſo much the worſe. There is a difference in the Promulgation; for ſome Laws may not be ſo clearly and fully made known to all the Subjects of 'em as others are, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66240:4"/>hence the breach of 'em may be the more pardonable and excuſable. There is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence alſo in the manner of a Man's tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing a Law: For he may do it wilfully and deliberately, and after many warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings given him, or upon little Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; or he may be ſurpriz'd into it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his general Purpoſe and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Now tho' every Tranſgreſſion of the Law of God may be truly ſaid to be a <hi>Work of Darkneſs,</hi> yet that name ſcarce uſes to be given to Sins of Infirmity or Weakneſs, to every Failing or Imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but rather to groſs and heinous Sins, When a Man may be truly ſaid to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs God's Law, becauſe he comes not up to the full perfection that it requires, or when in ſome leſſer Inſtances he unwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily and unwittingly offends, as by a raſh word ſuppoſe, an imprudent Action, a little miſ-ſpence of time, or not taking an opportunity to do all the good one might; Theſe tho' they are Faults and have the nature of Sins, yet the Scripture is hardly ſo ſevere as to ſtile theſe <hi>Works
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66240:5"/>of Darkneſs,</hi> except it be in the general, as belonging to that kind, and partaking in a degree of that nature. But that which moſt properly is to be underſtood by <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> is groſs and notorious Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, ſuch as are thoſe ſeveral kinds rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon'd up by the Apoſtle in the beginning of this Chapter; but more fully in the Fifth of the <hi>Galatians</hi> under the Name of <hi>Works of the Fleſh, Adultery, Fornication, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſciviouſneſs, Idolatry, Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, Hatred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions, Hereſies, Envyings, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Drunkenneſs, Revelling, and ſuch like.</hi> Here are Sins, you ſee, of all the three kinds, that are commonly reckon'd, <hi>i. e.</hi> againſt God, our Neighbour and our ſelves. 1. Here's Acts of Impiety towards God, ſuch as <hi>Hereſie,</hi> by which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly underſtood, and may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood here, Falſe and Wicked Opinions concerning God and Religion, Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Errors; <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or the Worſhiping falſe Gods, or the true one in a falſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden manner, a way diſhonourable to him; <hi>Witchcraft,</hi> or hold Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66240:5"/>with Evil Spirits, the Enemies of God. To theſe we might add Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and open Profaneneſs in Swearing or Curſing, as alſo groſs neglects of God's Worſhip, a general Indevotion, and cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary miſ-ſpending that time which ſhou'd be dedicated to God's Worſhip and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Again <hi>2ly.</hi> Here are Sins of Injuſtice or Uncharitableneſs towards our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, ſuch as are <hi>Adulteries, Murthers, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Variance, Emulations, Wrath, Strife, Seditions.</hi> And Laſtly, Here are Sins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ourſelves, or in the Government of our own Perſons, ſuch as <hi>Fornication</hi> (tho' that perhaps may be reckon'd alſo in the former kind) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, Laſcivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, Drunkenneſs, Revellings,</hi> and all manner of Intemperance.</p>
            <p>Now theſe and ſuch like groſs Sins are moſt properly to be underſtood by <hi>Works of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. I next proceed to give you the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons why they are ſo call'd. Now</p>
            <p n="1">1. One (and that a main reaſon) is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſuch Works as in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66240:6"/>general Opinion of Mankind are reckon'd vile and diſhonourable, and are wont therefore, many of 'em, to be forbidden by Humane Laws; And hence Men gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are both aſham'd and afraid to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit 'em in the open Day-light, or in the ſight and view of others: But if their evil Inclinations, or any Temptation prevail over 'em, ſo as to make 'em practiſe ſuch things, yet ſo long as they have any ſhame left, they creep into Corners, and ſeek to do it in the Dark, and hide their Wickedneſs all they can from the ſight of Men. Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>That they that are drunken are drunken in the night,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.7. And <hi>Job,</hi> That <hi>the eye of the adulterer waiteth for the Twilight, ſaying, no eye ſhall ſee me, and he diſguiſeth his face,</hi> Job 24. And ſpeaking of Thieves, ſays he, <hi>In the dark they dig through houſes, which they had marked for themſelves in the day time, they know not the light. For the Morning is to them as the ſhadow of death; if one know them they are in the terrors of the ſhadow of death.</hi> There is Fear indeed as well as Shame that hinders Men from
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66240:6"/>acting this ſort of Wickedneſs openly; and Shame itſelf indeed has always a mixture of Fear with it; it implies a fear of Diſgrace, and that curbs and checks Men, and keeps 'em from committing openly the more groſs and heinous ſort of Sins, and from glorying in 'em when they have committed 'em, unleſs they can meet with Companions as wicked as themſelves, or think themſelves too ſtrong for any that would oppoſe 'em. Men naturally love to have the good Opinion of others, and dread the being hated and abhorr'd of Mankind, which wou'd be the effect of many groſs and open ſorts of Wickedneſs. And therefore what they practiſe of that nature they endeavour to keep as ſecret as every they can: Yea many ſeem deſirous to hide their own Wickedneſs as much as poſſible even from themſelves, 'tis ſuch an odious and ſhameful thing. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they'll ſcarce dare to look into their own Conſciences, or conſider their own ways. They have ſo ill a Face, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch a Deformity in 'em, that they cannot well bear to look at it, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66240:7"/>they ſometimes invent to themſelves miſerable Excuſes, or take up moſt ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and abſurd Opinions, only to hide the uglineſs of their Vices, that ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd a Spectacle as their own Souls are, if ſeen in a true Glaſs, may not be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual Terror to 'em.</p>
            <p>Now 'tis true, that wicked Men are but Fools in all this, to think, that what they hide from Men, they can hide from the all-ſeeing Eye of God too; Or, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they can make a poor ſhift to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves a little, that therefore they ſhall be able to impoſe upon him, and blind his Eyes. And this therefore ſhews us another Reaſon why the Works of Wickedneſs may very well be call'd <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> Viz.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe they proceed from a dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Mind, a Mind that has ſome way ſhut out the Light, at leaſt, do's not ſuffer the Light of Truth to ſhine bright and clear as it ought to do. For the thing is ſo evident, That a Man ought to be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to the Laws of his Maker, and that all Sin is Unreaſonable in the higheſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66240:7"/>and extreamly Fooliſh; This, I ſay, is ſo evident, if a Man will conſider any thing, that he can hardly forbear ſeeing it. But Wicked Men therefore (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe that are ſo in an high and notorious Degree) are wont to be afraid of Thinking and ſerious Reflection, do not care to Examine impartially the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples on which they go, nor to compare their Actions ſtrictly with the Rule, but rather huddle up the Matter, and ſuffer their Luſts and Paſſions, or ſome Fooliſh and Licentious Notions, plauſibly ſet off perhaps, by the Wit of ſome of their Atheiſtical Companions, to darken and hoodwink their Underſtandings, ſo that they do not clearly diſcern the Folly and Unreaſonableneſs of their own Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, but go on in a blind and inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate manner; which is quite contrary to the way of good Men, <hi>Whoſe path,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. <hi>is as a ſhining light, which ſhineth more and more unto a perfect day.</hi> And hence it is, that ſuch in Scripture, are call'd <hi>the Children of Light,</hi> and <hi>of the Day,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.5.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66240:8"/>Whereas wicked Men are call'd, <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Darkneſs,</hi> as being ſuch in whom the <hi>Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> or <hi>the Ruler of the Darkneſs of this World,</hi> as he is call'd, hath blinded their Minds. Yea, they are call'd <hi>Darkneſs</hi> itſelf in the abſtract; at the 8th verſe of this Chapter. For the Apoſtle tells the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> That whilſt they were in their Heathen State, and liv'd Ungodly and Prophane Lives, they were <hi>Darkneſs. Ye were ſometimes darkneſs, but now are ye light in the Lord.</hi> And this Darkneſs which poſſeſſes the Souls of wicked Men, is ſo palpable and plain to all that have their Minds well enlighten'd with the knowledge of the Truth, that they cannot chooſe but wonder at it's prevalence, and admire the Sottiſhneſs, and Ignorance of thoſe that are ſo blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Whence it is, that the Pſalmiſt ſpeaks it by way of Admiration, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.4. <hi>Have all the workers of iniquity no knowledge?</hi> Implying, that a very little might have ſerv'd to ſhew 'em, That 'twas both their Duty and their Intereſt to act in another manner.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66240:8"/>
            <p> And thus the Works of Sin and Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, may be ſtyl'd <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> as proceeding from a darkned Mind. And they may be alſo call'd ſo,</p>
            <p n="3">3. From their tendency and aptneſs to darken it ſtill more and more. For this is certain, That nothing can more tend to cloud and darken the Reaſonable Soul, than an habitual Indulgence to ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices as are directly contrary to Reaſon, and ſuffering Brutiſh Luſts and unruly Paſſions to bear ſway and over-rule the Underſtanding. This is the direct way to extinguiſh, as far as it can be done, the Light of Reaſon, to put out that Candle of the Lord, as far as a Man is capable of doing it. And there want not thoſe who too plainly ſhew us, that it may be done in a great meaſure. They cou'd not elſe go on ſo ſecurely in their wicked Courſes as they do, if they had not gone a great way towards extinguiſhing the Light, and caus'd it to ſhine but very dimly; if they had not ſtifl'd the relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy of their Conſciences to the practice of Notorious Impieties. Nevertheleſs, 'tis
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66240:9"/>true, they cannot ſo ſtifle Conſcience, or put out the Light of their own Minds, as to ſecure themſelves, that it ſhall never trouble 'em no more. Conſcience will be awakened, and the Light will ſhine again, either happily here to bring 'em to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance before it be too late, or elſe to their endleſs Torment and Confuſion hereafter. Yea, there want not Inſtances of thoſe who have had their Conſciences thus awakened to terrifie and torment, and begin an Hell in 'em in this Life, without bringing 'em to a true Repentance. They being ſuch, as in the Apoſtle's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.27. have had <hi>nothing left 'em, but a certain fearful looking for of Judgment, and fiery Indignation, which ſhall devour the Adverſaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And this minds me of a 4th Reaſon why, works of Sin and Wickedneſs may be ſtyl'd, <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> viz. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe without Repentance, they will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly bring Men to that State of Wo and Miſery, which the Scripture calls by the name of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>outer Darkneſs.</hi> Whether to ſignifie its diſtance, and the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66240:9"/>Excluſion of thoſe that are there, from the Regions of Light and Glory Above; Or whether it be ſaid by way of Alluſion and carrying on a Metaphor. The Kingdom of Heaven, we know, is wont to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd to a Feſtival Entertainment, and is call'd <hi>The Marriage Supper of the Lamb,</hi> at which they who are Admitted, ſhall ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi> But it was the Cuſtom, at ſuch Feſtival Suppers, to light up many Lights in the Room, or Place where the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was. And then in compariſon with that, all without was very dark. And thereto the Phraſe of <hi>outer Darkneſs,</hi> may be ſuppos'd to allude. But be that as it will, 'tis certain, That as the Scripture ſets forth Almighty God, as dwelling in Light inacceſſible; ſo it deſcribes Hell, the Reſidence of the Prince of Darkneſs, as a Place void of Light, and tells us, That for Wicked and Ungodly Men, is reſerved <hi>the blackneſs of darkneſs for ever,</hi> Jude 13. Whether literally to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it matters not, ſo long as we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand by it, That 'tis a Region of Wo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66240:10"/>and Sorrow, as void of all Joy and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, as a total want of Light can make it. And this affords us therefore a 4th Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why, the works of Sin and Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, whoſe tendency is to bring us to this Place, may be ſtyl'd <hi>Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. I come now in the next place, to ſhew you why they are ſaid to be <hi>unfruitful works of darkneſs,</hi> and how well that Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Unfruitfulneſs agrees to 'em. The truth is, the terming 'em <hi>unfruitful,</hi> is (a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) a Figure whereby we ſpeak leſs than we intend ſhou'd be underſtood. For doubtleſs, our Apoſtle did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, we ſhou'd look on theſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> as only <hi>unfruitful</hi> and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as if that were the worſt that cou'd be ſaid of 'em, that they did us no good, ſince 'tis plain, by what has been ſaid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that they do us the greateſt miſchief. But his meaning therefore was, to inſinuate hereby to us, that as they bring us no good Fruit, are wholly <hi>unfruitful,</hi> as to that, ſo they are very fruitful of Evil and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66240:10"/>to us. 'Tis like what you read in the 7th. of <hi>Jer.</hi> v. 31. God ſays there of the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> That <hi>they built the high places of Tophet—to burn their Sons and their Daughters in the Fire, which I Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them not,</hi> ſays he. Whereby, He do's not intend (as ſome weakly enough wou'd infer, from ſuch kind of Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) to intimate, That Men ought not to do any thing in the Worſhip of God, which they have not an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for, from him, in his written Word. But the full meaning is, That He was ſo far from having Commanded it, that He had expreſly and peremptorily forbidden it, as the vileſt Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>I ſhou'd ſhew you therefore, how that this Character of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfruitfulneſs,</hi> agrees to the <hi>Works of Darkneſs</hi> in both ſenſes, both as it ſignifies a Barrenneſs, as to any true Good, and alſo as it may be here farther underſtood to imply, their productiveneſs of the greateſt Evil. But I ſhou'd be too tedious ſhou'd I go about to ſhew you this particularly concerning every one of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66240:11"/>'em. I ſhall therefore ſpeak but briefly, and in the general. Now, as the Duty of a Chriſtian conſiſts of three parts, <hi>viz.</hi> His Duty to God, to his Neighbour, and to himſelf. So Sin and Diſobedience (which are the <hi>Works of Darkneſs</hi>) may in like manner (as has been already inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated) be divided into Works of Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety towards God; Of Injuſtice or Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritableneſs to Men; Or elſe, Miſ-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Man's own Perſon.</p>
            <p>And Firſt, For Works of Impiety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, which are ſome of the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and fouleſt of the <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Blaſphemy, Profaneneſs, Total In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devotion,</hi> and neglect of all <hi>Religion, Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Swearing,</hi> and the like. What fruit can a Man expect to reap from theſe things? Theſe ſure bring neither Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure nor Profit with them. It muſt be a ſtrange Complexion of Soul that can cauſe a Man to take delight in this ſort of Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and a very great and unuſual ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, if he gains ſo much as any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral advantage by it. But this Fruit he is ſure to reap, <hi>viz.</hi> That whatſoever Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66240:11"/>befalls him, he has no God to go to, no Providence to put his Truſt in, no Hope nor Help left, unleſs he can change his Principles, repent, and become a new Man, which is one of the hardeſt things imaginable for ſuch People to do. Conſidering therefore how great Diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Calamities Human Nature is ever liable to, what Wiſe Man wou'd ever be without the Comforts and Supports of Religion under 'em? or wou'd not think it the moſt miſerable and forlorn Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be as without a God in the World? Which is the utmoſt (tho' the moſt vain and abſurd hope) of <hi>Atheiſts, Infidels,</hi> and <hi>Irreligious People.</hi> Thus you ſee the Firſt ſort of the <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> not only do us no good, but they ſtrip us of that which is our beſt and only Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and Comfort in a day of Trouble and Adverſity, even a good Conſcience and Hope in God, beſides that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign us over to endleſs Miſery.</p>
            <p>In the next place conſider what are the Fruits of Injuſtice or Uncharitableneſs. Why a little preſent Gain, or the quicker
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66240:12"/>getting of an Eſtate, is the moſt that can be pretended. But if we will allow others to be unjuſt too, and to act by the ſame Principles, we may ſoon loſe all that we have gain'd; And then we know not how ſoon we may come to want that Charity our ſelves which we deny to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their need. Beſides, if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there is a God, to whom Righteouſneſs and Goodneſs are eſſential, we can never ſure imagine he will ſuffer any Man to be finally a gainer by his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs or Unmercifulneſs, but will reckon with him ſeverely for it. And what a folly is it then to triumph for a little while in that which muſt unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have ſo wofull a Concluſion!</p>
            <p>The Third and Laſt ſort of <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> is that which conſiſts in the Miſ-government of our ſelves, thro' In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence to the Senſual Appetite. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which all I ſhall ſay at preſent is, That <hi>Epicuriſm, Voluptuouſneſs,</hi> with <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs in Eating and Drinking,</hi> as they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome fail to bring great Miſeries upon Men in this Life, in their Bodies, Eſtates
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66240:12"/>and Reputations; So foraſmuch as they wholly unfit Men for their Duty, and lay 'em open to all ſorts of Temptations, they cannot but be the ready way to endleſs Ruine and Miſery hereafter. And then they may very well according to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt ſenſe of our Apoſtle in the Text be ſtil'd <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfruitful Works of Darkneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I proceed now to the Fourth thing propos'd; Which was,</p>
            <p n="4">IV. To ſhew what is meant by having <hi>Fellowſhip with ſuch Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and what are the ordinary ways or ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Inſtances wherein Men may be tempted to have that.</p>
            <p>Now there are ſeveral ways wherein Men may be ſaid to have <hi>Fellowſhip with the Works of Darkneſs.</hi> As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. And moſt groſly, when a Man actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally joyns with others in any wicked Deſign or Practice. It may be he is not the firſt mover in it, but he is put upon it by others, and he concurs with them, and bears his ſhare. This is in the ſtricteſt ſenſe an having <hi>Fellowſhip</hi> or <hi>Partnerſhip</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:66240:13"/>with others in Wickedneſs. And this therefore is here ſtrictly forbidden in all caſes whatſoever. We are to have no <hi>Fellowſhip with the Works of Darkneſs,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with them. We muſt not think to excuſe our ſelves by ſaying, that we were drawn in by others, or that we comply'd with ſuch as wou'd have taken it ill of us if we had not, and whom we were loth to diſoblige. In all ſuch caſes, we muſt remember that of <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 1.10. <hi>My Son, if Sinners entice thee, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent thou not.</hi> Tho' there be never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, whatever Intereſt they may claim in us, be their Baits never ſo enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, or their Pretences never ſo plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, yet if we are ſatisfy'd that the thing they wou'd have us joyn with 'em in is Evil and Unlawful, we muſt by no means have an hand in it, but rather take the Advice which the ſame Wiſe Man gives us at the 15th verſe of the ſame Chapter, <hi>My Son walk not thou in the way with them, refrain thy foot from their path.</hi> Or as you have it at the 14th and 15th Verſes of the Fourth Chapter; <hi>Enter not into the path
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66240:13"/>of the Wicked, and go not in the way of evil men. Avoid it, paſs not by it, turn from it and paſs away.</hi> 'Tis good to keep at ſome convenient diſtance from it, leſt we be tempted, and unwarily fall into it. It is much better for us, that we ſhou'd be thought a little moroſe and ſowre, of an uncompliant and unyielding Temper, than to be drawn into ſinful compliances, or to bear a part in any thing that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtifiable and unlawful. But</p>
            <p n="2">2. We are not only then truly ſaid to have <hi>Fellowſhip with the Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> wheh we our ſelves are Actors in 'em, and joyn with others in committing 'em, cooperating together in the ſame unlawful Practices; But alſo when any way, by Word or Deed, we abet or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage any in Wickedneſs; when we ſhew 'em Favour or Countenance, give 'em any Direction or Counſel in it. In ſuch a Caſe, Tho' the ſinful Action be not our own, yet we make our ſelves Partakers in it; we have a ſhare in the Guilt, and muſt expect to have it alſo in the Puniſhment. It may be Caution or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66240:14"/>Policy may hinder Men ſometimes from acting that which is evil, but if they ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly abet or encourage it, however they may eſcape with Men, they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves guilty in the ſight of God. Yea</p>
            <p n="3">3. Not only the Poſitive encouraging and abetting of Wickedneſs by Word or Deed makes a Man Partaker in it, and renders him guilty of having <hi>Fellowſhip with the Works of Darkneſs.</hi> But the not hindring, not forbidding it, if he has Authority, not uſing his endeavour to diſcourage and diſcountenance it. For this every good Man is bound to do, even to ſet himſelf all he can, by his Example, and by his Authority, and by all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence he can tell how to have upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to promote Virtue and Holineſs, and to put a ſtop to the growth of Vice and Wickedneſs. And therefore 'tis not enough that we forbear what we believe to be evil our ſelves, and do not po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively abet and encourage others in the Practice of it, for we may do it tacitely and implicitely, by our Connivance, and by neglecting to admoniſh and reprove
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66240:14"/>ſuch as are under our care, not telling 'em of their Faults nor warning 'em of their Danger, nor ſhewing our ſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous of their forbearing ſinful Courſes and amending their ways.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, We may be ſaid to be partakers with others in Sin, and to have <hi>Fellowſhip with the Works of Darkneſs,</hi> when we knowingly, or careleſly, for want of reaſonable and prudent Caution in our Behaviour, give any ſcandal or offence to others, or lay any ſtumbling-block in their way, that may probably induce 'em to the commiſſion of any Sin. 'Tis eaſie to do this, by ſome ambiguous Words, or Deeds, that are liable to miſconſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or miſinterpretation. The greateſt Scandals indeed, are given by downright doing Ill, ſetting an ill Example before others, or joining in ſuch wicked and unjuſtifiable Practices as are apt to make Men ſpeak ill of the Profeſſors of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and endanger many's Apoſtatizing from it. <hi>And wo be to him by whom ſuch offence cometh.</hi> But there may alſo be Scandals given and Occaſions of Falling
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66240:15"/>ſet in the way of others by doubtful and ambiguous Words or Deeds, which tho' not Evil when rightly underſtood, yet may be very liable to miſconſtruction. And the truth is, no Man can be cautious enough, wholly to avoid giving Scandal to ſome or other, in this manner. But nevertheleſs, it is our Duty to uſe what Chriſtian Prudence we can, and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably may, to prevent any ſuch thing. And if we have, as we ought to have, a true love to our Brother's Soul, and a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der regard to the Intereſt of Religion, we ſhall uſe what Circumſpection we can to prevent any ſuch Evil. We ſhall, as the Apoſtle exhorts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Conſider one another,</hi> and mark each others Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, as far as we know how, to that purpoſe, <hi>that we may provoke unto Love, and to good Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus having ſhew'd you, what are the ſeveral ways wherein Men may be ſaid to have <hi>fellowſhip with the Works of Darkneſs,</hi> or may be tempted to make themſelves ſome way or other partakers in Wickedneſs; I proceed to that which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66240:15"/>was propos'd to be done in the 5th. place,</p>
            <p n="5">V. To ſhew, that Chriſtians ſhou'd have a care of being drawn in by any ſuch Temptations, and inſtead of that, ſhou'd upon all occaſions, ſhew their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſlike of theſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and be ready to reprove them. <hi>Have no fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with the unfruitful works of darkneſs, but rather reprove them.</hi> That this there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is a Duty, is evident enough from the plain Words of the Apoſtle, and from what has been already ſaid upon 'em But I ſhall Conſider the Arguments which he himſelf urges in this Chapter, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade to the Practice of it. The 1ſt. of which is, The Conſideration of that Dreadful Puniſhment, which unleſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by Repentance, muſt certainly overtake both them that work theſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> and thoſe alſo that have fellowſhip, or are partakers with them. To this purpoſe, he tells 'em at this 5th. Verſe, That <hi>no whoremonger, nor vnclean perſon, nor coveteous man, who is an idolater, hath any inheritance in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66240:16"/>Kingdom of Chriſt and of God:</hi> They muſt therefore be Excluded from the Kingdom of Heaven, and Sentenc'd to that <hi>everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fire, which is prepared for the Devil and his Angels.</hi> And becauſe ſome were ready to make frivolous Excuſes and Apologies for ſome of theſe Sins, as Fornication, in particular, which the Heathens made but a ſlight matter of, he adds therefore, at the Verſe next following; <hi>Let no man deceive you with vain words, for becauſe of theſe things cometh the wrath of God upon the Children of diſobedience.</hi> And then it follows, <hi>Be ye not therefore partakers with them.</hi> As much as to ſay, For if ye are, you make yourſelves acceſſary to their Damnation, and to all the ſore Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that may overtake them alſo in this Life. And as ye are partakers with them in their Sin, ſo you muſt expect alſo to be ſharers in their Puniſhment. The Argument therefore is exceeding ſtrong, and ſuch as if we have any regard either to the Soul of our Neighbour or our own Souls, muſt prevail upon us. If we wou'd not ruine them everlaſtingly,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66240:16"/>and ourſelves alſo with them, we muſt have a care of being partakers with 'em in Sin.</p>
            <p>There is alſo a Second Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment urg'd by the Apoſtle to the ſame purpoſe, in this Chapter, very fit to work upon Ingenuous Minds: And 'tis taken from the great Indecency that there is in Chriſtians (Profeſſors of ſo much Purity, and the Diſciples of ſo Holy a Maſter) having any thing to do with the <hi>Works of Darkneſs.</hi> Thus you read at the 3d. Verſe of this Chapter. <hi>But Fornication and all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs, or Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veteouſneſs</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which may ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie any inordinate luſting after, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring more than is convenient in any kind, and being plac'd here in ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, is by many Interpreters underſtood to ſignifie, not Avarice, but ſuch inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Luſts as occaſion'd Rapes, Inceſt, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> things too commonly practis'd at the Idol-Feaſts: But) <hi>let not theſe things be once nam'd among you,</hi> ſays he, <hi>as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh Saints.</hi> For ſuch all Chriſtians are, or ſhould be; and if they are not,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66240:17"/>their Chriſtianity will do 'em no good. And it becomes all ſuch to keep at the greateſt diſtance they can from all Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in Thought, Word, or Deed, and from all the Defilement of the <hi>Works of Darkneſs.</hi> And the ſame Argument in effect, is urg'd again, at the 8th. Verſe, to enforce the preceeding Exhortation <hi>(Be ye not therefore partakers with them) for ye were ſometimes darkneſs</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> in your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Heathen State) <hi>But now are ye light in the Lord</hi> (<hi>i. e.</hi> Ye have now had the Light of the Goſpel ſhining amongſt you, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been Baptiz'd into the Profeſſion of it, which is call'd, a being Illuminated, or Enlightened, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.32.) <hi>Walk there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as Children of Light.</hi> And let it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that there is a difference between your former, and your preſent Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Behave yourſelves as becomes thoſe that make ſuch a Profeſſion of Purity and Sanctity. And certainly, it is not fit for ſuch to have any thing to do with thoſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> before ſpoken of, but rather they ought by their good Example, to call Men off from them, and by ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66240:17"/>Admonition, and plain Reproof, where they have any Authority, or can reaſonably hope for any good ſucceſs, to endeavour to deter Men from ſuch Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, and to convince them of the great Folly and Danger of them; and upon all occaſions to be ready to ſhew their utter diſlike and Deteſtation of them. For in vain are they call'd <hi>The Children of Light,</hi> except they abhor the Deeds of Darkneſs. In vain are they Liſted, as the Soldiers of Chriſt, if they treacherouſly give Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to his Profeſs'd Enemies, or are aſham'd, or afraid to appear, upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, in the Cauſe of God and Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. And this brings me to the laſt thing that was propoſed, which was, To make ſome Application of the Doctrine that has been deliver'd to the preſent Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>Now the deſign of our preſent meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is to give what furtherance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement we can to that good Work, which out of an honeſt and Religious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66240:18"/>Zeal has bin undertaken and carried on with good effect, by many Pious and Well-diſpoſed Perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> The endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring as far as may be, by putting good and wholſome Laws in Execution, to ſuppreſs and put a ſtop to the <hi>Works of Darkneſs:</hi> Or at leaſt, to cauſe thoſe that will practiſe 'em, to keep themſelves, within their own proper Sphere, and act 'em in the dark and in private Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. What they do there, we muſt leave to the Judgment of God, who ſees 'em in their cloſeſt and ſecreteſt retirements, and will one day <hi>bring to light the hidden things of darkneſs,</hi> and take vengeance on all the Workers of Iniquity. But when theſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs,</hi> grow ſo Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, as to crawl abroad into the Light, they then greatly defile the Land, they ſhew Men to be come to a prodigious Pitch of Wickedneſs, and to have caſt off all ſenſe of Shame, and they involve all thoſe in a participation of the Guilt, that are Witneſſes to ſuch Wickedneſs, and do not all they can in their Places
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66240:18"/>and Stations towards the diſcountenanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſuppreſſing of it.</p>
            <p>Here therefore, Magiſtrates are chiefly Concern'd, to uſe all the Authority they have, Yea, to put it forth and exert it to the uttermoſt, in the Cauſe of God, and againſt open Prophaneneſs and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion. 'Tis from God, that all Juſt and Lawful Authority is deriv'd, and He will therefore, certainly expect it ſhou'd be us'd in his Service, and will look on them as no better than Traitors to him, that uſe it otherwiſe. Neither will it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for any to ſay, That they do Puniſh Vice and Prophaneneſs according to Law, when Delinquents are brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'em, and the Matter fully Prov'd, For this may be true; And yet they may be ready to diſcourage ſuch as wou'd bring 'em Informations. They may plainly ſhew an Averſion to the Work of Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and put many needleſs Rubs and Difficulties in the way of it, tho' they dare not openly and avowedly take part with Evil-doers.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66240:19"/>
            <p> But this is not like Men that have a Zeal for God's Glory, a ſenſe of the hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of Sin, of God's juſt Diſpleaſure againſt open and notorious Impieties and the Danger ſuch things bring a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into. This is not like the way of thoſe good Magiſtrates we read of in Scripture, who ſet themſelves with all their Might to carry on the Work of Reformation, and to prevent God's Judgments impending on the People. This favours not of any ſenſe that a Man has of their Blood being requir'd of him, who are miſled, or drawn aſide, or encourag'd in Sin by his Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. A Magiſtrate ſhould be a Man of Zeal and Courage and always glad of an Opportunity to ſhew himſelf <hi>A Terror to evil Works, and a Praiſe unto them that do well.</hi> For 'tis always to be obſerv'd, that we ſpeak now of putting Laws in Execution againſt ſuch things as are known and grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on all hands to be Evil; things which however ſome may endeavour to palliate and extenuate, yet none is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66240:19"/>ſo impudent as to juſtifie 'em, none ſo abſurd as to pretend to make Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of practiſing 'em. Some there are that have Scrupled the taking an Oath in any Caſe, but I never heard of any that thought it a Duty to Swear idſely in common Diſcourſe. Nor can Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs, or Tipling or Profaning the Lord's-Day, or Filthineſs, or Fornication, or Scoffing at Religion, and Ridiculing the moſt Sacred Myſteries thereof be pleaded for as Duties.</p>
            <p>If therefore Men will not be Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous againſt ſuch things as theſe, how can we hope to find any good Zeal in 'em? If they are grown indifferent as to ſuch Practices, and care not how much ſuch Vices ſpread, how can they be thought to have any Religion at all in 'em? If neither the Love of God nor of their Neigbour will excite 'em to ſet themſelves againſt ſuch notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and open Wickedneſs, what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence can they have to Chriſtian Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:66240:20"/>
            <p> But after all, tho' a Magiſtrate have a Senſe of theſe things and be Zealous for Reformation, yet 'tis but little that he can do without the help of others. Profane and Irreligious People, if once they find him bent againſt 'em, will take care to keep out of his way, and hide their Works of Darkneſs from his Sight. And there muſt therefore be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations given, and Proofs made by others, before he can do much to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards putting Laws in Execution againſt Vice and Profaneneſs.</p>
            <p>Now this is the Work which ſome here preſent, and many more both in this City and in other parts of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, have very laudably and worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engag'd themſelves in. The Work I am ſure is good and highly neceſſary at this time, when we are call'd upon by Publick Authority to do all we can towards the Suppreſſion of Vice, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality and Profaneneſs, which are own'd in his Majeſty's Proclamation to have encreas'd and prevail'd much of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66240:20"/>late Years to the great Diſhonour of God, the Scandal of our Profeſſion, and the endangering heavy Judgments to fall on us. And as the Work is ſo highly ſeaſonable, ſo I cannot ſee any good Objection, that is or can be made againſt it, or any juſt cauſe of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you engage in it through any other Motives, but a juſt ſenſe of the great need of it, and an Holy Indignation againſt thoſe <hi>Works of Darkneſs</hi> which every good Chriſtian muſt and ought to abhor.</p>
            <p>Shall any think it Pragmaticalneſs to meddle, when that which ought to be deareſt to us, the Cauſe of God and Religion is ſo nearly concern'd? When ſuch notorious Scandals are brought up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Profeſſion, and there is ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger of God's Judgments o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaking us by reaſon of our Impieties? As well we may think it Pragmatical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to endeavour to quench a raging Fire, or to put a ſtop to the Infection of a Contagious Diſeaſe. And 'tis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66240:21"/>but the want of a due ſenſe of the great Evil and Danger of ſuch groſs and heinous Sins, that makes any put a difference in theſe Caſes, and content themſelves with a Laodicean Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs in matters of ſuch Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</p>
            <p>But the Name of an Informer, is by many held in great Deteſtation, and they cannot bear the Reproach of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckon'd in that number. Now 'tis true, if the buſineſs were to inform againſt Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, otherwiſe innocent in their Lives, but Worſhipping God, according to their Conſcience, in a way not allow'd, and perhaps erroneous, I ſhou'd not blame a Man for being ſomewhat ſhy in ſuch a Caſe; Or if 'twere to be an Informer up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Penal Statues about indifferent Matters, however, all ſuch may not be to be condemn'd; yet I wou'd be no very zealous Advocate for 'em.</p>
            <p>But here the Caſe is quite otherwiſe. For here that which you are deſired to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66240:21"/>Inform againſt, is a known and confeſs'd Evil; and 'tis only in ſuch Caſes, when there appears no better way of reclaiming the Offender: And the End and Deſign of it, is not the getting any Gain to yourſelves, but the promoting a moſt needful Reformation, and the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby God's heavy Judgments from falling upon us all. 'Tis great Charity therefore to the Publick, Yea, and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity alſo to the Perſons Inform'd againſt (ſince gentler Methods will not do) to endeavour to have 'em Puniſh'd according to the Law. And if the Laws were well made, and but in purſuance of the Laws of God, it cannot but be a laudable thing in any one, to endeavour what in him lies, to have 'em put in Execution But ſtill, ſome will be ready to Object, That there's little hope of doing any great good this way. We may make a great ſtir and diſturbance among our Neighbours, but the World is not like to be much mended by any of theſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66240:22"/>
            <p> And this now is ſpoken like one whoſe Principle it is to let the World go as it will; but not like a Chriſtian, who knows 'tis his Duty to be as the Light of the World, and the Salt of the Earth. We know not how great Effects God may ſometimes bring about by Means that to us appear very unlikely, and improbable. But when He ſhall be pleas'd to ſtir up the Spirits of any Number of Perſons to go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſo Great and Good a Work as this is, I wou'd be loth to be found in the number of thoſe that ſhou'd ſlight and diſcourage it, and not rather do all they can to promote thoſe good Ends that Providence ſeems to have in it. Let us have a care we be not found Figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters againſt God. But I am ſure, all they who ſet themſelves to beat down Vice and Wickedneſs, and Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, are Fighters for him; and if they do it but in ſuch a way as is agreeable to the Laws of God and Man, they Fight Lawfully. And 'tis our Duty to help 'em, and pray for their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:66240:22"/>
            <p> There has already been, tho' not all the Succeſs that is to be wiſh'd for of ſo Pious an Undertaking; yet more perhaps, than cou'd well have been expected in ſo Corrupt an Age. And if God has any Mercy in ſtore for theſe Nations, and does not intend to give us up to Deſtruction, we have reaſon to hope, That this is the Way his Providence has found out to fit us for Mercy; And that He will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, more and more Excite a Spirit of Reformation, and ſtir up the Minds of all Religious and well-diſpos'd Perſons, of what different Perſuaſions ſoever, to join Unanimouſly in it. Which wou'd be an happy preſage of Good to theſe Kingdoms, Yea, to all the Churches of the Reformation: In which, the too great Unreformedneſs of Men's Lives, after ſuch a Reſtitution and Reviving of Pure and Primitive Chriſtian Doctrine, has doubtleſs, been the thing that has provok'd God to ſuffer the Reformation to loſe ſo much
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66240:23"/>Ground, as it has done of late Years, and to have ſuch a terrible Havock and Devaſtation made of it, and ſuch a Dreadful Perſecution of it's Profeſſors, as there is in our Neighbour Nation, and in other Places. The Conſideration of theſe things, ought, I am ſure, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken us, and cauſe us to Amend in time, and to do all that in us lies to promote a general Reformation, before Judgments overtake us.</p>
            <p>And may Almighty God in his great Mercy, encreaſe the Number, and ſtrengthen the Hands of thoſe Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Magiſtrates, that out of a true Zeal for his Honour, and the good of Men, do ſet themſelves with Heart and Hand to ſo Excellent a Work, and of thoſe alſo who are aſſiſtant and helpful to 'em therein. May He bleſs their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and give 'em ſuch Succeſs, that his Anger may be turned away from us, that we may become a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd People in our Lives, as well as in our Doctrine, and He may delight to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66240:23"/>dwell in the midſt of us. This is a Prayer, in which, <hi>The Children of Light,</hi> I am ſure, will heartily join with me <hi>And this God of his infinite Mercy Grant through</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>our Lord.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Matt. Wotton <hi>at the</hi> Three Daggers <hi>in</hi> Fleet-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>A Demonſtration of the Meſſias, in which, the Truth of the Chriſtian Religion is Defended, eſpecially a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> containing all that was Preach'd at the Lecture of the Honourable <hi>Robert Boyle,</hi> Eſq; By the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>Richard</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi> The 3d. and Laſt part now in the Preſs.</p>
            <p>—His Sermons Preached on ſeveral Occaſions. <hi>Oct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Guide to the Devout Chriſtian, in Three Parts; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Prayers for particular Perſons, for Families, and a Diſcourſe of the Sacrament. By <hi>John Inet</hi> Chanter of the Cathedral Church of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Chriſtian's Pattern, in Four Books; written Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally in Latin by <hi>Thomas à Kempis.</hi> To which are added, Prayers and Meditations for Sick Perſons; By <hi>George Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hope,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majeſty; In <hi>Octavo</hi> with Cuts, ſold for 5 <hi>s.</hi> The ſame Book Printed in a ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Letter. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Occaſional Papers, N<hi rend="sup">o</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</p>
            <p>The Heinouſneſs of Injuſtice; A Sermon Preached be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Mr. Juſtice <hi>Turton,</hi> at the Aſſizes held at <hi>Lincoln,</hi> 1698. By <hi>Laurence Echard,</hi> Chaplain to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remarks upon an Eſſay concerning Humane Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: In a Letter Addreſs'd to the Author. N<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1, 2, 3.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66240:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
